Guide to the Breed Collection of Maps, Documents, and Prints, 1545-1973
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- MAPS — SOLAR SYSTEM
  - Systema solari et planetarium ex hypothesi Copernicana..., a Iohanne Bapt. Homanno [Johann Baptist Homann, 1663-1724], Noribergae, undated; (20 x 23.5 | tinted) (191 (Map Case Drawer 15))
- MAPS — SOUTH AMERICA
  - Carte de la Terre Ferme, de la Guyane, et du Pays des Amanzones.. ., Par M. Bonne... A Paris, chez Lattre, a la Ville de Bordeaux, 1771; (15 x 20 | tinted borders) (069 (Map Case Drawer 13))
  - Description de Lima, Tom: VI, No. 32. Pag: 134, undated; (17.5 x 21 | black and white) (070 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Northwestern South America, including Peru and plan of Lima
    — Page illustrated with 2 maps and 2 engravings.
  - Kaart van het Onderkoningsehap van Peru zig uitstrekkende over Chili, Paraguay en anderen Spaansche Landen: also ook van Brazil en verdure Bezitting en van Portugal in Zuid – Amerika, Amsterdam by Isaak Tirion, 1765; (16 x 19 | tinted) (071 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — All of South America except nothern part above the equator.
  - Venezuela cum parte Australi Novae Andalusiae, Amstelodami, Henricus Hondius Excudit, 1636; (19.5 x 22.75 | black and white) (072 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Text in English on verso (pages 449-450): "The description of Venesvela... "
  - Paraguay, ó Prov. de Rio de la Plata cum regionibus adiacentibus Tucuman et Sta. Cruz De La Sierra, Amstelodami, Guiljelmus Blaeuw [Willem (Janszoon?) Blaeu] excudit, 1642; (18 x 21.5 | black and white) (073 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Text in Latin on verso (unnumbered pages): "Descriptio Paragvay... "
  - Venezuela cum parte Australi Novae Andalusiae, Amstelodami, Guiljelmus Blaeuw [Willem (Janszoon?) Blaeu] Excudit, 1642 (074 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Text in German on verso (page 20 and unnumbered page): "Venezvela."
  - Venezuela cum parte Australi Novae Andalusiae, Amstelodami, Ioannes Ianssonius excudit, 1666; (19.75 x 23 | black and white) (075 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Text in Latin on verso (unnumbered pages): "Venezvelae descriptio."
  - Mapa y Planta de Rio de la Plata Leventada y Emendada novamente por los Pilotos del Rey, Delineada y publicaca por el Senor Bellin, 1770; (18.5 x 25.5 | black and white) (192 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - The Coast of Caracas Cumana Paria and the Mouths of Rio Orinoco with the Islands of Trinidad Margarita Tabago Grenada and St. Vincent, by Thomas Jefferys Geographer to his Majesty... London, Laurie :& Whittle, 1794; (21 x 28 | black and white) (193 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - To the Right and Honorable Charles Earl of Sunderland... This Map of South America..., Herman Moll Geographer, [London], undated; (24.5 x 41 | tinted and decorated; folded; margins in poor condition) (220 (Map Case Drawer 16))
    — Inset: View of Potosi in Peru.
  - L'Amerique Meridionale ou la Partie Meridionale des Indes Occidentales... les provinces de terre ferme le Perous et le Chili... et le Brasil etc.. ., chez I.B. Nolin [etc.], 1704; (23 x 31.5 | black and white) (221 (Map Case Drawer 16))
    — South America.
  - Carthagena, Engraved for Luffman's Select Plans, Vol. II. London, Luffman, 1802; (8.5 x 11 | tinted) (224 (Box 2))
    — Showing the harbor.
  - South America, Engraved for Morse's American geography by A. Doolittle N.H. Published by Thomas & Andrews, Boston, undated; (9 x 8.25 | black and white) (232 (Box 2))
  - South America from the Best Authorities, Engraved by B. Baker Islington, 1800; (8.5 x 10 | black and white) (233 (Box 2))
  - Brasil Nuova Tavola, undated; (9 x 12.5 | black and white) (243 (Box 1))
    — In pencil: "Pirckheimer's Ptolemy 1562."
  - Amérique Méridionale, Par M. Bonne, Ingénier Hydrographe de la Marine, Liv. VII et X no.29. Andre sculp, undated; (9.5 x 13.75 | tinted boundaries) (259 (Box 1))
  - Tierra Nova, undated; (9 x 12.25 | black and white) (260 (Box 1))
    — Whole continent with only Castilla del Oro, Perv Provincia, El Brasil marked.
    — Text on verso (page 61): "Americae sive Perv... "
  - Pervviae Avriferae Regionis typos. Didaro Mendezio auctore, undated; (10.5 x 15.75 | black and white) (261 (Box 1))
    — Text in French on verso (page 9): "Le Perv."
    — In pencil: "Ortelius 1579."
  - Castilia avrifera cvm vicinis provinciis, 1597; (11.5 x 13.5 | black and white) (262 (Box 1))
  - Le Detroit de Magellan, Par le Sr. de Fer. A Paris..., 1700; (10.5 x 14.5 | tinted) (263 (Box 1))
  - An Accurate Map of South America Drawn from the Sieur Rober, Geogr. to the French King with Improvements, 1766; (8.25 x 13 | black and white) (264 (Box 1))
  - Map of the Countries on the South Sea from Panama to Guayquil, For the Rec. Dr. Robertsonis History of American. By Thomas Kitchin Senior Hydrographer to his Majesty, pub... by W. Strahan and T. Cadell, 1777; (10 x 15 | black and white) (265 (Box 1))
  - Brasilia, Johannes Blau [Joan Blaeu] Amsterdam, approximately 1645; (15 x 19) (283 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Latin text on verso.
  - Amerique Meridionale par N. Sanson d'Abbeville Geographe de Roy, Nicolas Sanson. Paris, 1650; (15.5 x 21.25 | outline handcolor) (285 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - Nova Hispania et Nova Galicia, G. Blaeu [Willem (Janszoon?) Blaeu]. Amsterdam, approximately 1640; (15 x 19.25) (286 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — No text on verso.
    — Map has been mounted to a backing sheet.
- MAPS — UNITED STATES
  - Carte de la Partie Méridionale des Etats-Unis, Pl. IX a la Fin du Tom. II., undated; (17 x 22.5 | black and white; poor condition) (076 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Virginia, Kentucky, North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia.
  - County map of the state of California, 1872; undated; (15 x 23 | tinted) (077 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Insets: City of San Francisco; San Francisco Bay and vicinity.
  - Partie Des Etats-Unis de l'Amérique Septentrionale, undated; (22 x 18 | black and white; poor condition) (078 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Western New England, N.Y. and as far south as South Carolina.
    — Small inset: "Canada Superieur et Inferieur."
  - The states of Maryland and Delaware from the latest Surveys, D. Martin sculpt., N. York. Pub. by John Reid, New York., [1795?]; (16.5 x 20.5 | black and white) (079 (Map Case Drawer 13))
  - Carte geopraphique des Provinces Neu York et Neu Jersey en Amerique, publié par les Heritiers de Homann 1778. Avec Priv. de Sa. Maj. Imperiale, undated; (20.5 x 24.5 | Black and white, with yellow boundaries and border) (198 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Shows parts of present New York, Vermont, New Hampshire, and Massachusetts, with Lake Champlain at the center.
  - Novi Belgii, Novaeque Angliae nec non partis Virginiae tabula multis in locis emendata per Nivolaum Visscher, undated; (19.5 x 25.5 | tinted) (199 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Facsimile? From Chagnon :& Co., Prints, Framing, French books, 26 West 46th Street, New York City, in 1939.
  - West Point and its Vicinity, 1866; (6 x 8 | tinted) (234 (Box 2))
  - Geological map of the country between San Diego and the Colorado River California, prepared in Office of P.R.R. Exp. & Surveys, By W. P. Blake, 1855; (7.5 x 10 | tinted) (235 (Box 2))
    — United States War Department.
  - An Accurate map of New York in North American from a late Survey, undated; (11.25 x 14.25 | colored boundaries, etc.) (266 (Box 1))
  - Map showing Moqui Indian Reservation and Pueblos and lines of the United States land surveys, undated; (9 x 11.25 | colored boundary lines) (267 (Box 1))
    — From 11th census, Indians.
  - United States, Edinburgh & Dublin, J. & F. Tallis, undated; (11 x 14 | colored boundaries) (268 (Box 1))
  - Virginia and Maryland, by Herman Moll Geographer, undated; (8.5 x 15 | black and white) (269 (Box 1))
  - Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware, undated; (9 x 11.5 | tinted) (270 (Box 1))
    — Must have been created after the inception of railroads.
  - Group of sketch maps of U.S. West, by U.S. Army, 1846-1847, undated (271 (Box 1))
    — [California coast from San Francisco to San Diego], June 19, 1847 (14 x 16; Inset: Lowe, California.)
    — Sketch accompanying Col. Price's despatch of 18 April, 1847 (8.75 x 10.25)
    — Sketch accompanying Col. Price's despatch of 15 Feb. 1847 (7.5 x 10; Showing Rio del Norte with Joya and Embudo.)
    — Sketch accompanying Col. Price's despatch (11.25 x 13; Pueblo de Taos at center.)
    — Sketch of the actions fought at San Pascal in upper California between the Americas and Mexicans, Dec. 6th & 7th 1846 (9 x 13)
- MAPS — WEST INDIES
  - A new general chart for the West Indies of E. Wright's Projection vut. Mercator's Chart..., London, undated; (18.5 x 23 | black and white) (080 (Map Case Drawer 13))
- MAPS — WESTERN HEMISPHERE
  - America, Drawn and Engraved for Thomson's new General Atlas, 1st. July 1813, (20.5 x 27.5 | tinted) (200 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - America Septentrionalis, Amstelodami, Excudit Ionnes Ianssonius [Jan Jansson, 1588-1664], 1623; (19.5 x 25.5 | tinted) (201 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Facsimile? See Novi Belgii, page 23.
  - Americae, mappa generalis..., Homonnianis Heredibus, 1746; (21 x 24.5 | tinted and decorated) (202 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - Americae Nova Tabula, Auct: Guiljelino Blaeuw [Willem (Janszoon?) Blaeu], undated; (19.5 x 25.5 | tinted) (203 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - Carte d'Amérique divisée en ses principaux états.. ., par J. B. Poirson... A Paris, chez Jean, 1798; (21.75 x 31.5 | colored boundaries) (204 (Map Case Drawer 16))
    — North America, South America, southwestern Europe, northwestern Africa.
    — Inset: Polar regions of North America.
  - Charte von America nach Olmedilla Arrowsmith, Azara, und andern guten Quellen entworfen, von F. W. Streit... Nurnberg bei Friedrich Campe, 1817; (23 x 29 | tinted) (205 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - A New and Exact Map of America laid Down from the Latest observations & Discoveries, [London] Sold by I. Bowles at Mercers Hall in Cheapside, undated; (24.5 x 40.5 | tinted; folded) (206 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Insets: Indian life, Niagara Falls, drying cod at New Foundland, and various harbour maps.
  - Novissima et accuratissima totius Americae, descriptio per I. Danckerts [Justus Danckerts, 1635-1701]. Amsterdam, [1688?]; (19.75 x 23.25 | black and white) (207 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - Novissima et accuratissima totius Americae, descriptio per N. Visscher (1623), [1973?]; (19.5 x 25.5 | tinted) (208 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — 1973 facsimile? See Novi Belgii, page 23.
  - Teâtre de la Gueue en Amerique telle qu'elle est à present Possedée par las Espagnols, undated; (20.5 x 24.5| tinted and decorated) (209 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Gulf coast, Mexico and Central America.
- MAPS — WORLD
  - Orbis Veteribus Notus, Drawn and Engraved from d'anville's Map of the Antient World.. ., [London] For John Harrison, 1788; (17.5 x 21.75 | black and white) (081 (Map Case Drawer 13))
  - [no title] National Atlas, page 44, Glasgow; Robert Weir – Lumsden & Son, Engraved by W & A.K. Johnston, undated; (13 x 21.5 | tinted) (082 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — One half of a world map.
    — Insets: coffee and sugar map, spice map, tea map, and sketches of Torrid Zone plants.
  - Basis Geographicae Recentioris Astronomica... Norimbergae: a Iohanne Gabriele Doppelmaiero... opera Ioh. Bapt. Homanni [Johann Baptist Homann, 1663-1724]..., undated; (20.5 x 24.75 | tinted) (210 (Map Case Drawer 15))
  - A new and correct Map of ye world, [London] Printed for and sold by Thomas Bowles..., undated; (24.5 x 40.5 | tinted; folded) (211 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Many insets and instructional materials printed in margins, including a map of the moon.
  - Planiglobii terrestris cum utroq hemisphaerio caelstri..., publice proponit Io. Bapt. Homann [Johann Baptist Homann, 1663-1724]..., undated; (20.5 x 24.5 | tinted) (212 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Both northern and southern hemispheres viewed from the poles.
  - A New and Correct Map of the World, Laid Down According To The Newest Discoveries, And From The Most Exact Observations, by Herman Moll Geographer, 1709; (24.5 x 41 | tinted and decorated; folded) (213 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Insets: moon, solar system, etc.
  - A Map of the World, on Mercators Projection, 1755; (8 x 12 | black and white) (236 (Box 2))
  - A Historic Map of the Roman Empire..., By Monsieur William Del Isle… Herman Moll.. ., 1709; (47.125 x 20.375 | tinted; folded) (276 (Map Case Drawer 15))
    — Inset: The world.
    — Some large tears and rips
- MAPS — MISCELLANEOUS
  - Castellania Aldenardensis, undated; (13 x 20 | tinted) (029 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Pages 47-48 of text with map at top of page 48.
    — Size refers to the size of the page, not the map.
  - Ditivncvla de Laleve, Vedasto du Plonich auctore, undated; (12 x 20) (038 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Pages 127-128 of text with map at head of page 128).
  - Coloniensis Archiepiscopatus, Auctore Ioh. Gigante medico et mathematico. Amsterdam, Blaeu [Willem (Janszoon?) Blaeu], undated; (19 x 22 | tinted) (040 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Text on verso (unnumbered pages).
  - Territorii Lendaviensis pars Septentrionalis, undated; (12 x 20 | tinted) (043 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Lindau in Bavaria (Germany)?
- MISCELLANEOUS PIECES
  - [Page of text:] L'Ancienne Germanie, (12.75 x 19.5) (004 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Printed on both sides of unnumbered page.
    — Lists of tribes, in old French, beginning with "Saxones."
    — See also map under Germany: Germaniae tabula denuo...
  - [Page of text in French] La Litvanie, Cimbrique, Briesve & nouvelle description de Lituanie, undated; (12 x 19.5) (005 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    —Unnumbered page of text, no maps.
  - Illustration of Atlas holding up the sky while standing on the globe of earth, from Frederick de Wit's Atlas, undated (006 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Text: "Bij Frederick de Wit in de Calverstraet bij den Dam in de Witte Poskaert."
  - [Title page] [Geographiae Blaviannae Volvmen tertivm Qvo Germania Qvae Est Europae Liber Octavvs continentvr, Amstelaedami, Labore & Sumptibus Ioannis Blaev [Joan Blaeu, 1596-1673], 1662; (11.75 x 20.25) (007 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Title page] Atlas, Amstelaedami, Chés I. B. Elwe, undated; (13 x 22.75 | decorated in color (008 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Title page] Neuer Atlas…uber die Ganze Welt..., von [Johann Baptist Homann, 1663-1724], Nuernberg, Verlegung des Auctoris, 1710; (12 x 20.5 | black and white) (009 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Title page] Atlas antiquus, sacer et profanus disposuit &emendavit tabulas, Joannes Clericus, Amstelodami, apud Petrum Mortier, undated; (12.5 x 19.75 | illustrated in color) (010 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Title page] Nieuwen Atlas ofte Weereldts – Beschrijvinge/ Vervolgh van't Tweede Deel. Inhoudende Vranckryck, en Hispanien, Amstelodami, apud Ioannem Ianssonium [Jan Jansson, 1588-1664], undated; (12.5 x 19.75 | decorated in color) (011 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [2 unnumbered pages from an atlas, no maps] Preface au Lecteur, undated; (19.5 x 23.25) (012 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Signed (in type): "Henry Hondius et Iean Ianson."
    — Size is of open pages.
  - Carte qui represente toutes les pieces qui sont comprises dans l'architecture militaire, ou l'art des fortifications.. ., Utrect, Casper Specht, 1703; (20 x 25 | black and white) (013 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Chart] Schematismus Geographiae Mathematicae, id est, repreasentatio figararum..., Norimbergae, Homann Heredum, 1753; (21 x 25.5 | tinted) (014 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - Genealogical chart of Eberhard Ludwig, Herzogen zu Wurtenberg und Teck... Augspurg, Matthaeus Seutter, undated; (21.5 x 26 | color) (018 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - Genealogical chart of Konigl. Hauss, Preussen, Familien Vorstell, Augspurb, Matt. [Seutter], undated; (22 x 25 | color) (020 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Images and extracted pages clipped from a volume on Australia], (27 pieces) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
    — In a large bag.
  - [Page of text in Italian] Descriptions of Tavola XLIV, XLV, XLVI, undated; (18 x 25.5) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
    — Pages 81-82.
  - [Pages of illustrated text in German] Plat VI, XXXIX, XLI, LVII, LVIII, LXX, LXXXII, undated; (7 sheets) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
    — Concerns both secular and Biblical personages.
    — Pages not consecutive.
    — Tied between heavy corrugated cardboard.
- DOCUMENTS
  - [Florida] By Peter Chester to Elias Dwenford, Surveyour-General, concerning land grant for Alexander Offutt, 1772 Feb 4; (Printed form with hand-drawn map attached. 2 sheets) (291 (Box 2))
  - [Florida] James Robertson, reduced Warrant-officer who had served in the siege of Quebec. Petition to Peter Chester, governor of West Florida, for land grant, 1777 Feb 3; (1 sheet) (291 (Box 2))
  - [Florida] Petition of Archibald Dalziel, a reduced Warrant-officer of his Majesty’s Navy … during the last war, for grant of lands due such Warrant officers in West Florida, approximately 1776; (1 sheet) (291 (Box 2))
  - [Florida] Pensacola [Fla.] to Peter Chester, governor of West Florida [1772-1777] for Tho. Hutchins by Alex. Dr. Macullogh his attorney [clerk of the Council of West Florida, 1776]. Petition for the renewal of Warrant for 200 acres, 1776 Apr 3; (1 sheet) (291 (Box 2))
  - [Florida] Renewal of warrant for land in West Florida for Thomas Jones. Signed by Gov. Peter Chester, 1776 Apr 17; (Printed form with hand-drawn map attached. 2 sheets) (291 (Box 2))
  - [Florida] Pensacola [Fla.] to Peter Chester, gov … by William Mackapern (?) for renwal of a warrant for 200 acres, 1776 Apr 22; (1 sheet) (291 (Box 2))
- PRINTS AND ILLUSTRATIONS
  Container list currently incomplete.
  - [Plate ] Sicilie... Foro di Vulcano... [Italy], Plate no. 4, undated; (14.25 x 19.5) (001 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Engraving of scene with fumaroles; spectators in foreground and approaching the vents.
  - [Plate]... Fabriche... della Citta di Cuma riedute da Mezzogiorno... [Italy], Plate no. 30, undated; (14.25 x 19.5) (002 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Engraving of ruins and caves with reaper and companion in foreground; other figures.
  - [Plate] Veduta delle Stufe ed Epitaffio di Tritoli, [Italy], Plate no. 15, undated; (14.25 x 19.75) (003 (Map Case Drawer 12))
    — Depicts ruins.
  - [Plate] Diana Efesina Trovata nelli scavi della Villa Adriana in Tivoli [Italy], Plate XXXII, undated; (18 x 25 | black and white engraving) (019 (Map Case Drawer 12))
  - [Print] Overwinnings Van Namen Syn Casteel, nieuwe Forten en Liniën; In't aansien van des Franfen Konings Leger, sterk 118000. Man. Door Willem de III. Koning van Groot Brittannien, etc., Amsterdam, Uytegegeven by Pieter Persoy, [1695?]; (24 x 30 | black and white) (090 (Map Case Drawer 13))
    — Battle scene.
    — MDCXCV may indicate date.
  - Bay of Naples, [Italy], Engraved for Luffman's Select Plans of the principal Cities, Harbours, Fortes etc. in the World, Vol. I, 1800; (8.5 x 11 | tinted) (230 (Box 2))
  - [Illustration] Akbar's Tomb – Secundra, Drawn by W. Purser; engraved by J. Rolph, undated; (7.25 x 11.) (237 (Box 1))
  - Colored print of Niagara Falls. By J. & F. Tallis, London, Edinburgh & Dublin, undated (MISSING AS OF 2019)
  - [12 prints of Northeastern United States scenes, mostly New York State, by W.H. Bartlett, 1837-1839; (8 x 10.625 | color) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
  - 5 miscellaneous lithographs, etc. of New York City and vicinity, undated; (4.5 x 6.5); (4.5 x 7.125); (7 x 9.5) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
  - [37 Illustrations] from The History of the Indian Empire, 2 vols, undated; (7.5 x 11) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
    — Three scattered signatures of text included: pages 293, 296-298; pages 329, 332, 333, 336; and pages 385-392.
    — In envelope.
  - [Print] Regent Street… [London], No.79 of R. Ackerman's Repository of Arts, 1822; (6 x 9.5 | color) (MISSING AS OF 2019)
    — In separate envelope.